John Milt Morris Cartoons
John Milt Morris Cartoons
1960-1968
Morris, Milt, 1906-1994.
1.3 linear ft.
190 original editorial cartoons produced for the Associated Press.
2651143
Biographical History
John Milton Morris (1906-1994), also known as Milt Morris, was an American cartoonist.
John Milt Morris was born in Santa Barbara, California in 1906. As a teenager, Morris was involved in an accident that left him in bed for an extended period of time. During his recovery, Morris spent his time drawing.
Morris’ first job after high school was in the morgue at the Los Angeles Herald Express. Morris pursued art classes at night and was able to transfer to the art department. At age 23, Morris moved to New York City, where he struggled to find a job during the Great Depression until being hired at the New York Journal American. Five years later in 1935, Morris began working for the Associated Press.
In the 1940s, Morris filled in for editorial cartoonist Henry "Hank" Barrow and when Barrow left the Associated Press in July 1949, Morris replaced him. During his career as an editorial cartoonist, Morris traveled to Washington D.C., often with other cartoonists, to draw caricatures of the president currently in office. Morris spent over 50 years with the Associated Press.
In addition to editorial cartoons, Morris also drew Oscar Hitt’s panel cartoon, Neighborly Neighbors and he worked on the comic strip Scorchy Smith. Morris was a member of the National Cartoonists Society and he won the 1956 National Headliners Club Award.
John Milt Morris died on May 1, 1994 from pneumonia.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John Milt Morris Cartoons contain 190 pieces of original artwork for editorial cartoons produced for the Associated Press from 1960 to 1968. Morris' work focuses on national and international affairs. Frequent topics in this particular collection include the civil rights movement and urban riots, the Vietnam War including issues related to the draft and demonstrations, obscene reading materials and entertainment, and the Soviet Union.
Morris worked in ink and crayon on illustration board. Cartoons measure 12" x 14". Captions are typed and pasted on. Dates are written on the back in pen. Morris' name and address is also stamped on the back of each.
Arrangement of the Collection
Cartoons are arranged in chronological order.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Morris, Milt, 1906-1994.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Associated Press.; Art -- Cartoonists; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Editorial cartoons -- United States.; Civil rights movements -- United States -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Strikes and lockouts -- Caricatures and cartoons.; World politics -- 1945-1989 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1945-1989 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoons (humorous images); Editorial cartoons.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of John Milt Morris, 1969.
Inventory
- Cartoons, Click here for a detailed inventory.; See below for an index to the cartoons.; 190 items 12" x 14"
  - Jan 1960, Mar-May 1960 (Oversize 1, Folder 1)
  - Jun-Dec 1960 (Oversize 1, Folder 2)
  - Jan-Jun 1961 (Oversize 1, Folder 3)
  - Jul-Oct 1961, Dec 1961 (Oversize 1, Folder 4)
  - Jan-Feb 1962, Apr-Jul 1962 (Oversize 1, Folder 5)
  - Aug-Nov 1962 (Oversize 1, Folder 6)
  - Feb-Aug 1963 (Oversize 1, Folder 7)
  - Sep-Dec 1963 (Oversize 1, Folder 8)
  - Jan 1964, Mar-Apr 1964, Jun-Jul 1964, Sep-Oct 1964, Dec 1964 (Oversize 2, Folder 1)
  - Mar-May 1965, Jul-Sep 1965 (Oversize 2, Folder 2)
  - Oct-Dec 1965 (Oversize 2, Folder 3)
  - May-Jun 1966, Aug 1966, Oct-Dec 1966 (Oversize 2, Folder 4)
  - Jan 1967, Mar-May 1967 (Oversize 2, Folder 5)
  - Jul-Aug 1967, Oct-Nov 1967, undated (Oversize 2, Folder 6)
  - Jan-Mar 1968, May-Jul 1968 (Oversize 2, Folder 7)
Index to cartoons
The following is a list of predominant people, places and subjects appearing in the editorial cartoons in this collection. The list is not exhaustive. Some subjects may require you to browse with alternative terms.
B= Box, F= Folder. For example: B1F1= Box 1 Folder 1.
Africa B1F2 B1F8
Alabama B1F7-B1F8
alcohol B1F7
Algeria B1F1 B1F6
Arkansas B1F7
armed forces B2F2 B2F5 B2F7
Asia B1F8
auto industry B2F1 B2F6
automation B1F3
Berlin B1F3-B1F5
Berlin Wall B1F8 B2F4
Black Power B2F6
Brezhnev, Leonid Ilyich B2F4
budget B1F8 B2F4 B2F6
business B1F2 B2F1
capital punishment B2F2
capitalism B1F6
Castro, Fidel B1F3 B1F5-B1F6 B1F8
China B1F3 B1F6-B1F7 B2F3-B2F5
Churchill, Winston B1F5
civil defense B1F5
civil rights B1F1-B1F2 B1F5 B2F5
Cleopatra (movie) B1F7
communism B1F1 B1F3-B1F6 B1F8 B2F3
Congo B1F3
Congress B1F2 B1F7 B2F4
Cuba B1F6-B1F7
de Gaulle, Charles B2F2-B2F4
Democratic Party B1F2 B1F6 B2F7
demonstrations B2F3 B2F6
disarmament B1F7
draft B2F3 B2F5
drug use B1F6 B2F6
Eisenhower, Dwight B1F1
elections B1F2 B1F5 B2F4 B2F6-B2F7
Erhard, Ludwig B1F8
Estes, Billie Sol B1F5
Europe B2F4
Ford, Gerald R. B2F2
France B2F2 B2F4
free enterprise B1F8
free press B1F8
Fulbright, J. William B2F2
Germany B1F8 B2F4
gold B2F7
government spending B1F3 B2F1
graduates B2F5
Great Society B2F4
gun control B2F7
Hammarskjold, Dag B1F3
Hitler, Adolph B1F3
Ho Chi Minh B2F3 B2F5-B2F6
holidays B1F6 B2F3
Hoover, Hebert B2F1
hunger B1F5
India B1F6
inflation B1F5 B2F4 B2F6-B2F7
Iraq B1F7
Japan B1F1
Johnson, Lyndon Baines B1F8-B2F2 B2F4 B2F6-B2F7
journalism B1F7
judicial system B2F3
juvenile delinquency B2F2 B2F5
Wilhelm II (Germany) B1F3
Kennedy, John F. B1F1-B1F8 B2F5
Kennedy, Robert F. B2F2
Khrushchev, Nikita B1F3-B1F8
Kosygin, Alexey B2F3
labor B1F4
Laos B1F7
MacArthur, Douglas B2F1
McNamara, Robert B2F1
Medicaid B2F2
Middle East B1F7 B2F6
minimum wage B1F3
Mississippi B1F7
Monroe, Marilyn B1F6
Morse, Wayne B2F2
Nasser, Gamal Abdel B1F7
national debt B1F7
Nazism B2F4
Nehru, Jawaharlal B1F6
New York City B2F1
Nixon, Richard M. B1F1-B1F2 B1F4 B2F7
nuclear weapons B1F1 B1F3-B1F7
peace B1F2 B1F7 B2F3
police B2F1
pollution B2F1
population B1F5
pornography B1F7
poverty B2F2
power outage B2F3
Powers, Francis G. B1F2
Princess Margaret B1F1
prisoners of war B2F2
profanity B1F7 B2F2 B2F7
propaganda B1F6 B2F7
racial violence B1F7-B1F8
racism B2F6
railroad industry B1F1 B1F7
Reagan, Ronald B2F5
religion B1F5
Republican Party B1F2 B2F1 B2F7
riots B2F6
Rockefeller, Nelson B1F1-B1F2
Romney, George W. B2F7
Roosevelt, Eleanor B1F6
Russia B1F4 B1F6 B2F3-B2F4
school dropouts B1F7
schools B1F5 B1F7
shipping industry B1F3
smoking B2F1
socialism B1F1
South Africa B1F1
Soviet Union B1F2-B1F3 B1F6-B1F7 B2F2 B2F4 B2F7
space exploration B2F3
steel industry B1F1 B2F1-B2F2
strikes B1F1 B1F3 B1F7 B2F1-B2F2 B2F6
Syria B1F7
Taft Hartley Act B1F3
taxes B1F5 B1F7 B2F4 B2F6
tourism B2F4
traffic fatalities B1F6 B2F4
transportation B1F5
U.S. Postal Service B2F7
unemployment B2F1
United Auto Workers B2F1
United Nations B1F2 B1F5-B1F6 B1F8 B2F3
Venezuela B1F8
Vietnam War B1F4 B1F6 B2F1 B2F3-B2F7
violence B2F2 B2F5
voting B1F2 B2F3
Wallace, George B2F7
Warren Commission B2F4
water supply B2F2
World's Fair B2F1
Zedong, Mao B2F4-B2F5